Guide to the Bailey Willis Papers SC0200
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bailey Willis papers
circa 1900-1962
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Willis, Bailey
SC0200
1 Linear Feet
Collection includes diagrams from Appalachian structures labeled "Experiments in Folding"; a pamphlet "Bailey Willis Speaks"; two typescript papers on geology, 1944 and undated; report on the San Andreas Fault Valley, ca. 1933; report of the Golden Gate Bridge & Highway District regarding Willis' criticism of the bridge foundation and his comment on the report, 1934-35; biographical materials, 1949-62; and a manuscript poem by Willis, 1939.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
In part, gift of Branner Earth Sciences Library, 1979.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
After early studies in Germany, Bailey Willis attended Columbia University and was awarded the degree of Mining Engineer in 1878 and of Civil Engineer in 1879. In 1884 he began his career with the United States Geological Survey, working chiefly in the Pacific Northwest. He made geological research trips to China and Argentina, before coming to Stanford University in 1915 to succeed John C. Branner as head of the Department of Geology. Willis was a popular teacher and lecturer and taught at Stanford until his retirement in 1922.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes diagrams from Appalachian structures labeled "Experiments in Folding"; a pamphlet "Bailey Willis Speaks"; two typescript papers on geology, 1944 and undated; report on the San Andreas Fault Valley, ca. 1933; report of the Golden Gate Bridge & Highway District regarding Willis' criticism of the bridge foundation and his comment on the report, 1934-35; biographical materials, 1949-62; and a manuscript poem by Willis, 1939.
Golden Gate Bridge (San Francisco, Calif.); San Andreas Fault (Calif.); Appalachian Mountains.; Willis, Bailey; Willis, Bailey; Stanford University. Department of Geology. Faculty
- Papers
  - Diagrams from Appalachian structures labeled "Experiments in Folding" and a pamphlet "Bailey Willis Speaks" (Box 1)
  - Biographical memorials, 1949-62 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Aaron C. Waters, "Memorial to Bailey Willis," Geological Society of America Bulletin, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Resolution [Stanford], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Continental Drift, typescript paper, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Golden Gate Bridge & Highway District, 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report of Building Committee, Investigation of Criticism of Foundation by Dr. Bailey Willis, 1934 (2 cc) along with letter and comment by Willis, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Growth of the Earth as an Abode of Life, typescript lecture to California Academy of Sciences, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellany: genealogy chart (?) and letter regarding transfer of materials to Stanford University Libraries, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Poem, "The Borrowed Gown," possibly read at Stanford commencement, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - San Andreas Fault Valley, report by Willis, ca. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photocopies of letters by Willis to a nephew and niece, 1941-47, and photocopy of a Christmas card to relatives [originals held by Nell Scruggs] (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2017-336
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey drawings of preliminary values for movements of triangulation stations in California between 1906 and 1922., 1923 Jun (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Willis from the Chief Bowie of the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, 1924 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)